Guide to the Libby Gilbert Zine Collection, 1986-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Libby Gilbert Zine collection 1986-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Gilbert, Libby.
3.0 Linear Feet 112 Items
Zine collector and publisher. Gilbert's zines include The Ten Condiments (1988-1989) and Ancient Grandma Secrets (1990-1997).
Collection includes Gilbert's zines, acquired through trade, purchase, or self-publishing. Most zines focus on music or culture. Collection is arranged alphabetically by zine title.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Libby Gilbert Zine Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Biographical and Historical Note
A native of Oregon, Libby Gilbert attended college there and later spent three years in Tucson, Arizona, where she continued to publish Ancient Grandma Secrets, before relocating to central California to pursue a career in science.
Collection Overview
In February 2012, Libby Gilbert donated her personal collection of music zines and magazines, comprising 47 different titles and over 100 issues in total. Originally obtained through trade, purchase, or self-publishing, the titles in her collection span the years 1981-1996, and the common thread is the underground rock music scene in the United States and abroad, with particular focus on the Pacific Northwest, where she lived during much of that time. In 1988 and 1989, she published music and poetry zine The Ten Condiments with Kaija Campos (then Kaija Berleman), and later published her own music zine, Ancient Grandma Secrets, from 1990-1997. During the 1980s, her favorite musical sub-genre was second-wave garage psychedelic rock. To this day she remains a sucker for a well-crafted melody.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Gilbert, Libby
Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States
Self-publishing
Underground press publications -- United States
Zines -- United States -- Periodicals
Zines -- Music -- United States
Young women -- United States -- Social life and customs
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Zines and Magazines, 1986-1995, (4 boxes)
  Collection Arrangement
  Materials have been arranged alphabetically by zine title, with one title per folder. A few oversize zines have been housed in Box 4.
  - Ancient Grandma Secrets, 1990-1997 (Box 1)
    By Libby Gilbert. Music zine. 6 Issues: 5-7, 9-11. Location: Pacific Northwest, Tucson AZ, San Francisco, CA.
  - Backlash, June 1989 (Box 1)
    Weekly music paper. 1 Issue: June 1989. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle, Oregon.
  - Ben Is Dead, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 11. Location: Hollywood, CA.
  - Blatch, 1987 (Box 1)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 13. Location: Norman, OK.
  - BraveEar, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    Underground music zine. 3 Issues: Vol. 3, no. 2, 5, and 6. Location: Berkeley, CA.
  - Bucketfull of Brains, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    Underground music zine. 3 Issues: 16, 18, 20. Location: London, England.
  - Chemical Imbalance, 1987 (Box 1)
    Underground music zine. 1 Issue: 6. Location: New York.
  - Chronicles of Disorder, 1996 (Box 1)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 1. Location: Schenectady, New York. Patti Smith issue.
  - Contrast, 1987 (Box 1)
  - De'Pressed Int'l, 1993 (Box 1)
    Underground culture magazine. 1 Issue: 1. Location: Detroit, MI.
  - Edgeworks, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    Music zine. 2 Issues: Vol. 1, issues 4-5. Location: Pacific Northwest, Portland.
  - Feminist Baseball, 1987 (Box 1)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 8. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle.
  - FlipSide, 1987, 1991 (Box 1)
    Underground music zine. 2 Issues: 54, 70. Location: Whittier, CA. #54 is 10-year anniversary issue.
  - Forced Exposure, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    Underground music zine. 4 Issues: 11-14. Location: Waltham, MA.
  - Fuzz Buzz, 1989 (Box 2)
    Fuzztones band zine. 1 Issue: The Return Of.... Location: Beverly Hills, CA.
  - Girl Trouble, 1988 (Box 2)
    "Official Girl Trouble Program." Location: Pacific Northwest, Tacoma, WA.
  - Growing, 1989? (Box 2)
    Music and art zine. 1 Issue: 6. Location: West Valley City, UT.
  - High Times, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    "Recreational" magazine. 3 Issues: Aug. 86, Oct. 86, Aug. 87. Location: Mt. Morris, IL. Includes musician cover stories.
  - Incite!, 1989-1998 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 10 Issues: 15, 19, 21-23, 25-28, 30. Location: Cambridge, MA.
  - Ipso Facto, 1988 (Box 2)
    Underground culture magazine. 1 Issue: 5. Location: San Francisco, CA.
  - It About, 1991 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 1. Location: Greenville, IL.
  - Jet Lag, 1986 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 2 Issues: 69, 72. Location: St. Louis, MO.
  - Matt Lukin's Legs, 1987? (Box 2)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 4. Location: Pacific Northwest, Eugene, OR.
  - Maximum Rock & Roll, 1991 (Box 2)
    Underground music magazine. 1 Issue: 94. Location: Berkeley, CA.
  - Nothing, date unknown (Box 2)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 4. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle. Hand-painted cover.
  - Paper Toadstool, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    Music and art zine. 2 Issues: 1, 2. Location: West Valley City, UT. From publishers of Growing zine.
  - Parker's Bark, 1986 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 2 Issues: 2, 3. Location: Pacific Northwest, Portland.
  - Pimp, 1989 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 1. Location: Austin, TX.
  - Scam, 1994 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 11. Location: Houston, TX.
  - Snipehunt, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    Music zine. 3 Issues: 88(1?), 2, 4. Location: Pacific Northwest, Portland.
  - Tand, 1989 (Box 2)
    Fashion and poetry zine. 2 Issues: 1, 2. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle. #2 includes short story by Libby Gilbert.
  - Terminal Report, late 1980s (Box 3)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 2. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle. Drugs issue.
  - Thang!, circa 1988 (Box 3)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 10. Location: Brookline, MA.
  - The Bob, 1986-1996 (Box 4)
    Underground music zine. 19 Issues: 27-30, 32-35, 37, 38, 45-48, 50-53. Location: Wilmington, DE.
  - The Ledge, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
    Music zine. 7 Issues: 11-17. Location: Cincinnati, OH.
  - The Punchline, 1988 (Box 3)
    Music and culture zine. 1 Issue: 2. Location: San Francisco, CA.
  - The Pushcart War, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    Music zine. 2 Issues: Nov. 1989 and Jan. 1990. Location: Pittsburgh, PA.
  - The Rocket, 1991 (Box 4)
    Local music monthly. 1 Issue: 44. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle.
  - The Ten Condiments, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    Music and poetry zine. 3 Issues: 1-3. Location: Pacific Northwest, Seattle. By Kaija Berleman and Libby Gilbert.
  - The Ugly American, circa 1988 (Box 3)
    Music zine. 1 Issue: 2. Location: Pomona, NJ.
  - The Village Noize, 1994 (Box 3)
    Underground music magazine. 1 Issue: 17. Location: New York. John Spencer cover.
  - Thicker, 1994 (Box 3)
    Underground music magazine. 1 Issue: 2. Location: San Francisco, CA. John Spencer cover.
  - Thrill!, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
    Music zine, band Crayon. 5 Issues: 2, 4, 7, 9, 11. Location: Pacific Northwest, Bellingham, WA.
  - Total Abandon, 1981 (Box 4)
    Underground music and art zine. 1 Issue: 8. Location: Pacific Northwest, Portland, OR.
  - True Reality Rock Report, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    Newsletter; later a music zine. 3 Issues: 1, 6, 9. Location: Pacific Northwest, Eugene, OR.
  - Vicious Hippies from Panda Hell, 1990-1992? (Box 3)
    Music zine. 11 Issues: 4-14. Location: Pacific Northwest, Portland.
  - Your Flesh, 1991, 1992 (Box 3)
    Underground music magazine. 3 Issues: 23, 24, 25. Location: Minneapolis, MN.